Good morning everyone. I am admitting
everyone from
the waiting room. So, good morning
everybody as people are joining on in
and there's a few other individuals
joining.
We are just letting everybody in from
the waiting room. So, good morning.
Happy Tuesday everybody. This I'm
Dominick Zerlo with the New Mexico
Department of Health Center for Medical
Cannabis and psilocybin. And
we're just here this morning for the
patient qualification and safety
committee for the medical psilocybin
advisory board.
This meeting is being recorded. So, just
as a reminder please keep language
in to be acceptable for public review
as we will be posting the meeting up
onto our website here down the road.
Just also to let everybody know we've
reminded people during several meetings.
But it doesn't hurt to remind again is
the department and actually all
executive agencies for the state are
going through an ADA American with
Disabilities
Act update. And so our websites are
taking a little bit longer to get
information on. So, please be patient
with us as we get that process
handled and items updated.
So, thank you. It may take a little
longer than usual just with that going
on. But we're trying to make sure that
happens in a as quick a time as
possible. And with that I'd like to turn
the meeting on over to the chair Ian
Dunn. And so with that Ian, the meeting
is yours.
>> Alrighty, good morning everyone. Welcome
to today's meeting. It is the patient
qualification and safety committee.
Today we're going to be going over how
to add new conditions within this
committee setting.
There's many inputs and um research that
has already been collected by a few
individuals, so I wanted to give them
the opportunity to
present that information and um
you know,
get to it faster than I have to
reacquire that information and draft
each new um qualifying condition.
So, what we will go ahead and go ahead
and look at is our guidance for new
qualifying conditions. This is what's
going to go ahead and allow us to do
that. But first, I'm going to let anyone
who would like to participate today
introduce themselves at this time.
>> All right, and if you'd like to
introduce yourself, you can definitely
drop something in the chat um and you
can also raise your hand with the icon
at the top that has a hand and says
raise
um and we will unmute you from there.
All right, and we've got Don Moser's
hand up.
Um and Don, I have enabled your mic. You
can unmute when ready.
>> Great, just uh a quick good morning. I'm
Don Moser. I live in Las Vegas, New
Mexico
and I've enjoyed learning about this new
program very much and uh
thank you for including me.
>> Awesome, thank you Don.
Um let's see and then the chat we've got
Sky Rivers uh with Santa Fe Reporter and
Ellen Schimmels, uh psych mental health
nurse practitioner in Albuquerque.
And let's see, I see James Brown's hand
up and James, your mic is enabled. You
can unmute.
>> Morning everyone. Uh James Brown, uh
doctor pharmacy here, New Mexico. Uh
thank you again for having these
meetings. Ian, thank you again for this
chair.
Um I'm representing 5 Degrees North
Healing Foundation, a nonprofit in here
in New Mexico.
Um just excited to participate. Thank
you.
>> Awesome. Thanks, James. And in the chat
we've got Kate Hawk, uh, psychedelic
trauma therapist and educator from Santa
Fe.
All right. And also in the chat, uh,
Hanifa Nayo,
um, co-director of the psychedelic
mental health access alliance. And
Gregory Evans, Gregory Evans.
All right. Not seeing any more hands up.
And just last in the chat, we got
Catherine Warnock. Uh, good morning uh,
from Las Cruces.
And
uh, and Hanifa's in Santa Fe. Cool.
Cool. Cool.
>> All righty well, thank you everyone for
being here and taking the time to
introduce yourselves. So, what we
already have agreed on in this committee
is what we are going to accept in terms
of um, qualifying conditions and
petitions after that um, January 31st
deadline. So, what we're going to do
today is work on the standardized format
for our recommendations here. We've done
a few um, already that we've worked on
and adopted. So, we could kind of get
the flow of what they need to look like.
But, this will be the formal way to
allow anyone from the committee to
submit and say, "Hey, I want to add this
qualifying condition. Here are my
clinical trials." And then
here's the recommendation.
Um,
and that just allows for a more
expediated process. I know different
organizations and different groups of
people um, have different priorities in
terms of the patients that they serve,
and so it would allow them to use any
information that they've compiled to
help us out in this program in any way
possible. Uh Jorge, if you could uh
share your screen
or
for the guidance.
>> Okay, almost there.
>> Perfect, no worries.
The other one in the same folder.
Leslie, it's the other um document. It's
titled guidance for qualifying
conditions.
>> Sorry about that, almost there.
I think I got it.
>> Perfect. All righty, so here is kind of
the format of how we would go and then
um of how each one would look. You would
email your request with the subject line
PQS NQC and then what your new condition
or symptom cluster would be.
It would have um
a very simple format. It would be
whereas the impact the qualifying
condition has
and whereas randomized clinical trial
one, whereas random clinical trial two
and then evidence for the mechanism
behind effectiveness and then additional
points as needed.
With the standard, therefore, the
committee finds that the current body of
clinical and systemic and mechanistic
evidence supports the inclusion of a new
condition and symptom cluster as a
qualifying condition within a regulated
evidence-based psilocybin services
program.
Um we would have that minimum of three
different peer-reviewed research studies
with a reference to a current DOI. That
way it would be accessible by the
department and the board um without
needing to actually send over, you know,
a 30 40 50 page research paper. Um
which is a little bit more burdensome on
our systems to handle.
So uh I will open any discussion,
questions, comments, concerns on this
one.
Yeah, Ellen.
>> Okay, there we go. And you should be
>> I got it. Thanks. Yeah. Um I'm just
curious if there's any um
anything specific about the level of
research that you're asking about or is
it just any peer review? So it could be
like a like a single case study or
something like that? Or is there going
to be parameters to what level of
research study?
Thanks.
>> So the two um it would be two randomized
clinical trials um and then an evidence
or mechanism would be the specific like
tiers of research that we would need. Um
so
that's the preference in terms of like
a case study that would be used as like
additional points as needed, but we
would preferably have randomized
clinical trials in assessing safety and
um
effectiveness.
>> So so I guess with the with the
randomized control trial one two, that
would be like a third one could be
something like a case study.
For your third, you're saying three
peer-reviewed research studies?
>> Yeah, so it would be those two and then
it would be a third. It could have been
the mechanism, it could be a case study,
it could be
whatever additional points you feel
would help
the argument or feel is necessary for
the board to consider in reviewing that
condition. Um
those would could be provided as well.
>> Great, thanks.
>> All right, I see Kate Hawk's hand up and
you uh should be able to unmute.
>> Yeah, thank [clears throat] you
everybody. I'm just wondering is this,
you know, three randomized or three
published peer reviewed studies? Is this
a guideline or is this really going to
be a strict rule? You know, we just know
that random um
like placebo controls are very tricky in
this area and sometimes there's very
promising studies but not three peer
reviewed. Like there may be one even
here in New Mexico that's looking good
but hasn't been published yet. So, I
mean this all seems nice if it's
available but you know, there are some
things that would probably be
um justified but there may not be this
quality of of studies at this point.
>> Yeah, and um one of the things that I
went through in trying to craft this, I
actually went back a couple of years
into the medical cannabis program and
reviewed there um
why certain recommendations were
rejected. And among them, the most
common was there was no randomized
clinical data available. Um my goal is
not to shorten down the list and prevent
people from having access. My goal is to
make sure that um if we send something
to the the department it gets approved.
Um
And so that's why that's there. I do
think there's only two
two clinical trials that we require for
this guideline
of what we accept within the committee.
Of course, the committee could
determine, you know, there's a rare edge
case and we need to
say, "Hey, this might need something."
But in terms of
what is typically approved, we like to
have
at least one or two clinical trials and
then some third that can be a
mechanistic, that can be
um
like a case study, that could be
you know, observational reports. But
typically from what I've seen from the
medical cannabis program, we need at
least a few clinical trials.
>> Okay. Yeah, also I'm assuming this is
going to be
just medical psilocybin, not actually
mushrooms since there's so little
research so far on mushrooms.
>> Um
I believe
under the medical psilocybin act it is
actually on mushrooms for the purposes
of the randomized clinical trials, we
will accept research on psilocybin
because it's
research on psilocybin or psilocin
because both break down into the same
thing in the body while having
differences in duration of action and
onset intensity. They often have a
similar neuroplastic
neuroplastic effect. But I do see
Dominic's hand up if you had better
clarification.
>> Yeah, thank you, Ian. I just in general,
just so that everybody knows is yes, in
the past because the way the statute is
set up that it they are additional
conditions that are recommended by the
advisory board and accepted by the
secretary of the department. And that's
the same setup that we have had for
medical cannabis historically and this
has been across pretty much every
secretary that I've worked with since
the beginning of the program. The
requirements are always that there needs
to be that scientific research, that
peer-reviewed research and that without
having that the items and and the
conditions are not accepted. Um the
exception for that was when the medical
cannabis uh program first started in
that first year or two, there were
several different conditions that were
accepted based on anecdotal evidence.
And it's actually been with some of
those conditions that there has been
additional research with potential
negative effects and where we have had
other individuals saying why actually
were these particular conditions
approved when it was just on anecdotal.
And so the secretaries after that really
tightened the requirements and really
said there have to be studies. And I
should note that it's not just about um
that there's a benefit in the immediate.
It also really does need to look at
long-term. And while there's not a lot
of research yet regarding psilocybin
long-term for some of these conditions,
that's something where with uh and once
the research fund gets funded, that's an
area where some of those areas that do
not currently have a lot of
peer-reviewed research that's been
published could potentially actually
still have patients who are involved
through that research fund aspect. And I
know that was discussed in the board
meeting last week about, you know,
ensuring uh with well, with regard to
funding. And so um hopefully there will
be funding for that down the road so
that we can actually help not just with
treating patients, but also with
expanding the research and ensuring that
the
that the that the different conditions
are appropriate to be treated with
psilocybin. So, I hope that's helpful.
But, the other side is if there's not
the research there,
historically the secretaries reject them
the even if the board adopts a
recommendation for a condition, the
secretaries have then rejected that
recommendation. And so, we do need to
make sure that that is that those are
things that are included in. Now, as to
specifically because I think what you
were asking wasn't just if it was
mushrooms, but also if it was with
regard to synthetic psilocybin. And I
think that would be something that
that could be
definitely could be utilized, but I
think it would be the strength of the
trial itself. So, the power of the trial
and of the results with it. So, I
wouldn't rule that one out. We would
just need to see whether or not or or
what those trials and what that
peer-reviewed research actually shows.
So, I hope that helps clarify things
somewhat.
>> Yeah, and just to kind of
oh, piggyback just a little bit
in terms of what that additional piece
the reason why I chose for listing
purposes mechanism was because if you
can show the mechanism of why psilocybin
works, then we can say then it's not
just because it's a psilocybin synthetic
molecule, it's the psilocybin in these
mushrooms as well. Um, but anyway, sorry
Katherine I for interrupting you.
>> No, that's okay. I'm you know, I'm just
wondering about randomized clinical
trials being the only acceptable. I
understand peer-reviewed and we want
good quality research. Um, but you know,
even in the FDA phase one studies uh,
that I was just working on in at
Scottsdale Research Institute, everybody
knew they were getting mushrooms. Uh,
you know, the the whole placebo thing is
it's like people have tried and they're
it's still, you know, not uh, very
realistic. But, uh, this is good
clarification. Thank you.
>> [snorts]
>> All right. And next, uh, we've got Lida
Fatemi and your mic should be enabled to
unmute.
>> Thank you so much. I want to, uh, say
how excited I am for this as a
physician. Um, I think this is so
exciting that we can bring in other
diagnoses other than what's, you know,
set out in the bill. And, um, just so
excited for this for our patients. And
thank you for putting this together.
>> Yeah, of course. Thank you all for being
here.
>> All right. And next, we've got Eileen
Brewer and your mic is enabled to
unmute.
>> Hey. Yeah, I just wanted to say that I
think that this format for, um,
the considering different conditions is
excellent. As like you guys asked me
last time to put together some
information about pain, which I did. But
as I was doing that, I was really
concerned by the, you know, there's a
lot of different pain conditions and
trying to capture all of that
information. But so much of it was,
here's a huge body of anecdotal
evidence, but no randomized controlled
trials or a very small pilot study or,
um, just a case study,
um, within a broader context of
anecdotal evidence in in a in a write-up
about the condition. And I was like,
there's got to be some like
just we're going to have to pick what we
want to look at as far as evidence. And
I think that this is a really good way
to to choose. And I know like I'm I'm a
traitor to my group because I I live in
the headache community.
And so the evidence, while I know that
it works for people living with
headache, the evidence might not
actually be there on paper. And so I I
agree the health department is going to
look at what evidence is there on paper.
They're not going to look at anecdotes
because there's not there's often not
enough information. And I think that
this is a really good concise way to go
out looking at it. I love that you
include mechanism behind it, although
there might be multiple mechanisms
behind it. So people will have to list
those out, but I just think this is a
great job and I want to say thanks.
>> Awesome. Thanks. And next we've got
Hanifa.
And Hanifa, your mic is unable to
unmute.
>> Awesome. Good morning everyone.
Um this is a a wonderful uh formula and
process. Super excited to be learning
about it. I'm curious around
um the the timing of it. Is this going
to be a process that's ongoing
um or are there uh time boundaries
associated with this process?
>> So with this specific process, so what's
going to happen is um
people that participate in these
committees um that have
uh
interest in the program and want to you
know develop it
are going to be the first ones to kind
of work on compiling this evidence um
and getting these first um additional
group of qualifying conditions out
there. So this would be until January
1st is when this committee owes its
deliverable back to the board of their
list of qualifying conditions that we've
eventually gone through.
Um this is what allows us to add
conditions to that list. So, as we bring
up and you guys send more new qualifying
conditions to um that email address,
then they will get
sent out to committee members that are
signed up for their next meeting.
Um and then at that meeting, we'll go
into more detail, discuss it, hear from,
you know, the person that actually wrote
the email,
um
and you know, what they're trying to
say, see if the wording fits, and, you
know, that kind of thing. And then we
would
um
you know, either adopt it or not,
depending on, you know, the specifics
and the condition and evidence.
But after that process,
um and beginning in February of 2027,
um there will be a petition process
where you will petition directly to the
board to add new conditions.
>> And that petition is open to the public
or only people who are part of the
subcommittees?
>> Uh the public.
>> Cool. Thank you so much.
>> Mhm, of course.
>> All right. And James Brown, your mic is
enabled. You can unmute.
>> Let me start. Um I really like this
process, Ian. Thank you for bringing
this to the committee.
One of the things I think we need to
really kind of talk about is the
validity,
you know, side of it. Kind of Dom-
Dominic brought it up as far as that.
Um you know, case-based trials or
case-based studies are something we
really need to look at with a filter of,
you know, that harm reduction. These
things are one-time things.
And yeah, they can be looked at as great
individually,
but I think we really need to look at
those randomized clinical trials as a
part of
the validity and being able to apply
those
in medical based program. And so, I
think
you know, getting case based is great,
but I think we've really [clears throat]
got to use caution
when you look at cases and say
what actually happened
and what didn't happen.
Um and can we use that maybe in a trial?
You know, but I really think we need to
stick to the trials and more
of the sample sizes need to be larger
than the number one.
And so, um just an FYI on that.
Um
Also, I think um
I I really like the committee's idea of
bringing things like pain, headaches,
GI things, um other things to this
committee
cuz there's a new clinical trial out
there right now that came out a study
from JAMA
that just came out. It's really
beneficial.
And it talks about depression. And it
actually has a lot of validity.
And so, I really wanted to throw that
out there. Uh things like that, we need
to have that process
to review it as a committee
so that we can get these other
conditions included.
Thank you again.
>> Thank you, James. And thank you for
bringing up that um new study. I hadn't
gotten the notification yet, so I am
excited to check that out.
All ready. So, if we are um
okay with this format, then what I will
go ahead and do
um
is leave it to committee members. Um
How long would you guys like to
until our next meeting to start
preparing these new um PQS
new qualifying conditions so that we can
get the ball rolling?
Uh Dominic?
>> I Ian, what I would recommend, and this
is just based on timing since these
conditions aren't going to be considered
until after January, is uh I would
recommend giving um a little bit of time
uh for people to be able to get things
together. I know a lot of people who are
involved in this particular committee
also are involved with various
institutes of higher education here in
New Mexico and are probably getting
their first break that they've had in
the last 10 months. And so maybe looking
at something about 6 weeks out or maybe
even 2 months um with regard to giving
people time to do the research and look
at it, and also take a little bit of
time for themselves.
>> Yeah, so how does everyone feel
July 6th?
Cuz that's 1 2 3 6 weeks?
>> Uh the only thing I would say on that
Ian is for many people that is um
they'll be celebrating the July 4th
weekend and I would not recommend doing
uh having something on that Monday as
some people may be traveling and taking
advantage of that extra day off.
Um but perhaps the week after?
>> the 13th?
>> That's what I was thinking.
>> Cool.
Already. Well, I appreciate everyone
taking the time to be here and just to
review the format. Um
I assume once, you know, the ticket is
in and
IT updates that it'll be available on
the medical psilocybin website for you
guys to review. Make sure you have
everything and then get it buzz on over.
I will go ahead and we will consider
them as a committee in the order that
they're received. So
um
if you send in pain on Monday and trauma
on Tuesday, we'll go pain and then
trauma. Um and yeah, but thank you all
so much for being here on an early
Monday morning and spending the first
part of your morning with us.
>> Thank you, everybody.